{
  "title": "Data_Structure - Binary_Search_Tree — Slot 2 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Binary_Search_Tree — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is the tightest upper bound that represents the time complexity of inserting an object into a binary search tree of n nodes? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(1)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O( log n)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>O(n log n)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1416/gate2013-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>The average depth of a binary search tree is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{0.5})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O(\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n \\log n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O(\\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52839/isro2011-62\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>How many distinct binary search trees can be created out of 4 distinct keys? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>14</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>24</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>35</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>14</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/18134/isro2011-11\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>We are given a set of n distinct elements and an unlabeled binary tree with n\nnodes. In how many ways can we populate the tree with the given set so that it\nbecomes a binary search tree? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>n!</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\( \\frac{1} {n+1} .^{2n}C_n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>1</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2131/gate2011-29#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The following numbers are inserted into an empty binary search tree in the given order: 10, 1, 3, 5, 15, 12, 16. What is the height of the binary search tree (the height is the maximum distance of a leaf node from the root)? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>6</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1001/gate2004-4-isro2009-26\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Suppose the numbers 7,5,1,8,3,6,0,9,4,2 are inserted in that order into an initially empty binary search tree. The binary search tree uses the usual ordering on natural numbers. What is the in-order traversal sequence of the resultant tree? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>7 5 1 0 3 2 4 6 8 9</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0 2 4 3 1 6 5 9 8 7</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9 8 6 4 2 3 0 1 5 7</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/909/gate2003-19-isro2009-24\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>How many distinct BSTs can be constructed with 3 distinct keys? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3387/gate2008-it-73\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>A Binary Search Tree (BST) stores values in the range 37 to 573. Consider the following sequence of keys.<br><br>\nI.   81,537,102,439,285,376,305<br>\nII.  52,97,121,195,242,381,472<br>\nIII. 142,248,520,386,345,270,307<br>\nIV.  550,149,507,395,463,402,270<br><br>\nWhich of the following statements is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I, II and IV are inorder sequences of three different BSTs</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I is a preorder sequence of some BST with 439 as the root</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II is an inorder sequence of some BST where 121 is the root and 52 is a leaf</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>IV is a postorder sequence of some BST with 149 as the root</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>II is an inorder sequence of some BST where 121 is the root and 52 is a leaf</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3386/gate2008-it-72\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A Binary Search Tree (BST) stores values in the range 37 to 573. Consider the following sequence of keys.<br><br>\nI.   81,537,102,439,285,376,305<br>\nII.  52,97,121,195,242,381,472<br>\nIII. 142,248,520,386,345,270,307<br>\nIV.  550,149,507,395,463,402,270<br><br>\nSuppose the BST has been unsuccessfully searched for key 273. Which all of the above sequences list nodes in the order in which we could have encountered them in the search? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>III only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3385/gate2008-it-71\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The cost of searching an AVL tree is \\(\\Theta (\\log n)\\) but that of a binary search tree is \\(O(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The cost of searching an AVL tree is \\(\\Theta (\\log n)\\) but that of a complete binary tree is \\(\\Theta (n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The cost of searching a binary search tree is \\(O (\\log n )\\) but that of an AVL tree is \\(\\Theta(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The cost of searching an AVL tree is \\(\\Theta (n \\log n)\\) but that of a binary search tree is \\(O(n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>The cost of searching an AVL tree is \\(\\Theta (\\log n)\\) but that of a binary search tree is \\(O(n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3272/gate2008-it-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>You are given the postorder traversal, P, of a binary search tree on the n\nelements 1, 2,...,n. You have to determine the unique binary search tree that has\nP as its postorder traversal. What is the time complexity of the most efficient\nalgorithm for doing this? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\) (logn)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\) (n)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\) (nlogn)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above, as the tree cannot be uniquely determined</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\) (n)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/458/gate2008-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>When searching for the key value 60 in a binary search tree, nodes containing the key values 10, 20, 40, 50, 70, 80, 90 are traversed, not necessarily in the order given. How many different orders are possible in which these key values can occur on the search path from the root to the node containing the value 60? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>35</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>64</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>128</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>5040</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>35</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3462/gate2007-it-29\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that we have numbers between 1 and 100 in a binary search tree and want to search for the number 55. Which of the following sequences CANNOT be the sequence of nodes examined? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>{10,75,64,43,60,57,55}</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{90,12,68,34,62,45,55}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>{9,85,47,68,43,57,55}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>{79,14,72,56,16,53,55}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>{9,85,47,68,43,57,55}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3588/gate2006-it-45\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A binary search tree contains the numbers 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8. When the tree is traversed in pre-order and the values in each node printed out, the sequence of values obtained is 5,3,1,2,4,6,8,7. If the tree is traversed in post-order, the sequence obtained would be <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8,7,6,5,4,3,2,1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1,2,3,4,8,7,6,5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,6,7,8,5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,7,8,6,5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,7,8,6,5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3816/gate2005-it-55\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>The numbers \\(1, 2, .\\dots n\\) are inserted in a binary search tree in some order. In the resulting tree, the right subtree of the root contains p nodes. The first number to be inserted in the tree must be <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>p</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>p + 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>n - p</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n - p + 1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>n - p</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3757/gate2005-it-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}